Neeraj Varshney

Ph.D. Student (4^{th} Year) Computer Science (NLP/NLU) Arizona State University

Research Interests

Efficient & Reliable NLU Systems
Open-Domain QA
Selective Prediction
Learning from Less Supervision
Multi-task Learning
Generalization
Reasoning
Learning from NL Instructions
Robustness

Collaborators

Chitta Baral (ASU)
Swaroop Mishra (ASU)
Pratyay Banerjee (ASU)
Tejas Gokhale (ASU)
Man Luo (ASU)
Arindam Mitra (Microsoft Research)
Daniel Khashabi (Allen AI)
Ashwin Kalyan (Allen AI)
Peter Clark (Allen AI)
Yizhong Wang (Allen AI)
Rik Koncel-Kedziorski (Alexa AI)

Coursework

Natural Language Processing Statistical Machine Learning Artificial Intelligence NLP Methods in BioMedical Knowledge Representation Data Mining Social Media Mining Mobile Computing

Technical Skills

PyTorch, Transformers
Pytorch-lightning
Spacy, Huggingface
Data Analysis, Pandas, NumPy
Git, Mechanical Turk
Matplotlib, NLTK, word2vec

OTHERS

- Reviewer for EACL'23 (in QA).
- Published 15+ ML/NLP articles on medium with $70,000^+$ views.
- Worked with Dr. Ayush Choure and Dr. Prateek Jain (MSR, India).
- Coordinator of CS Association at BITS Pilani and organized Research Talks event.

Research Statement

I work in Natural Language Processing, primarily in the areas of Open-domain QA, NLI, improving Efficiency & Reliability of NLP systems, and NLU in general. On the efficiency topic, I have worked on improving inference efficiency, training sample efficiency, QA reader efficiency, knowledge indexing efficiency, and evaluation efficiency. On the reliability topic, I have worked on selective prediction. My work has been published at premier conferences including ACL, EMNLP, EACL, NAACL, AAMAS, and AAAI.

Selected Projects

(1) Can Open-Domain QA Reader Utilize External Knowledge
Efficiently like Humans?

KNOWLEDGENLP, AAAI, 2023

(2) Unsupervised Natural Language Inference Using PHL Triplet Generation ACL, 2022

(3) On Efficiently Indexing External Knowledge for Open-QA

UNDER REVIEW@AC

(4) Investigating Selective Prediction Approaches Across Several Tasks in IID, OOD, and Adversarial Settings

(5) ILDAE: Instance-Level Difficulty Analysis of Evaluation Data

ACL, 2022

(6) NumGLUE: A Suite of Mathematical Reasoning Tasks

ACL, 2022

ACL, 2022

Email:nvarshn2@asu.edu

Website: nrivarshney.github.io

Semantic Scholar: Neeraj-Varshney
LinkedIn: neerajvarshney97

(7) Towards Improving Selective Prediction Ability of NLP Systems REPLANLP, ACL, 2022

(8) Let the Model Decide its Curriculum for Multitask Learning DEEPLO, NAACL, 2022

(9) Model Cascading: Towards Jointly Improving Inference Efficiency and Accuracy of NLP Systems

EMNLP, 2022

(10) On Reliably Re-Attempting the Unanswered Instances of the Selective Prediction System

UNDER REVIEW@EACL

(11) Benchmarking Generalization via In-Context Instructions on 1,600+ Language Tasks

EMNLP, 2022

(12) On Evaluating NLP Models' Understanding of Feasibility

EACL, 2023

(13) An Architecture for Novelty Handling in a Multi-Agent

Stochastic Environment: Case Study in Open-World Monopoly

AAAI SYM. 2022

Work Experience

Amazon Science May 2022 - Aug 2022

Applied Scientist Intern

Worked in the Web Question Answering team for Alexa AI.

Microsoft Jan 2018 - July 2019

Software Developer

• Worked towards developing a machine learning driven chat recommendation system aimed at augmenting user engagement with the product Microsoft 'Teams'.

Education

Arizona State University 2019 - 2024 EXPECTED

Ph.D. in Computer Science

• Advisor : Dr. Chitta Baral

CPGA: 4/4

• Awards: GPSA Award (2 times), Graduate College Award (4 times), SCAI conference award (2 times), ACL 2022 registration award from Repl4NLP, AAAI 2023 student scholarship.

BITS Pilani, Pilani Campus, India 2014-2018

B.E (Hons) Computer Science

- CGPA: 9.11/10
- Experience: 'Web Intelligence & Social Computing' research lab under Prof. Poonam Goyal, CEERI research lab under Dr. J.L. Raheja.
- Internships: Microsoft, Samsung R&D Institute, Valuefirst Digital Media.